Guide to the June D. Drake photographs
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
June D. Drake photographs
1860-1955
1900-1955
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Drake, June D., 1880-1969
Org. Lot 678
28.26 cubic feet 71 document cases; 2 slim document cases; 1 oversize flat box (11x14); 2 oversize flat boxes (6x20); 1 oversize flat box (20x24); 1 oversize folder
This collection consists of photographs taken by June D. Drake and the Drake Bros. Studio. They primarily document the town of Silverton, Oregon, and surrounding areas from approximately 1900-1955. Includes portraits of townspeople and views of businesses, streets, organizations, and homes in Silverton and vicinity, as well as Mount Angel and Salem, Oregon, and photographs of agriculture, the lumber industry, and transportation, among many other subjects. Of special interest are Drake's photos of the area now known as Silver Falls State Park, which he helped to establish.
Collection is open for research.
Gifts of June Drake from 1959-1964 (Lib. Acc. 8030; Lib. Acc. 8106; Lib. Acc. 8142; Lib. Acc. 8418; Lib. Acc. 8571; and Lib. Acc. 8722). Also includes additions from various small accessions between 1958 and 1984.
Negatives by June D. Drake are viewable online in OHS Digital Collections.
This collection is arranged in the following series:
Series 1: June D. Drake family, circa 1900-1930
Series 2: Portraits, circa 1889-1952
Series 3: Locations, 1860-1953
Series 4: Agriculture, circa 1887-1955
Series 5: Davenport family, 1868-1953
Series 6: Native Americans, 1908-circa 1930
Series 7: Lumber industry, 1890-1948
Series 8: Military, 1918-1940
Series 9: Transportation, 1890-1950
Series 10: Animals, 1920-1934
Series 11: June D. Drake historical collections, 1946, undated
Series 12: Copy work, 1881-1950, undated
Series 13: Negatives, 1860-1955
June D. Drake (the middle initial "D" did not stand for anything) was born in Marquam, Oregon, in 1880 to Charles Wesley Drake and Fannie Aurora Milster Drake. In the fall of 1889, the Drake family moved to Silverton, Oregon, and Charles Drake built the family home at 401 South Water Street. He later owned the Commercial Hotel on Main Street, which was sold in 1891 to hardware store owner Adolf Wolf. Charles Drake also served as mayor of Silverton before his death in 1911.
In 1900, June D. Drake and his brother, Emory Roy Drake, founded their photography business, Drake Bros. Studio, buying out the business of pioneer Silverton photographer William L. Jones. The brothers operated their studio together until 1908, when Emory Drake left to become a music teacher in Sacramento. This studio burned to the ground on March 27, 1908, and thousands of the brothers' original negatives were destroyed. After the fire, members of the Silverton community built June Drake a temporary studio at 311 North Water Street. He operated his business there from April 1908 until September 1911, when he moved into a new studio building at 303 North Water Street. Drake continued his photography there until his retirement in 1960, when the building was sold to Standard Oil Co. and torn down.
Though he was well known for his portraiture and town scenes, one of June D. Drake's greatest achievements was the establishment of Silver Falls State Park. Beginning around 1902, he photographed the waterfalls and created brochures and booklets to bring statewide attention to the need to protect the land from logging interests. Working with Silverton and Salem citizens and Oregon state legislators, Drake organized an effort to buy the land around the falls and sell it to the state. On April 2, 1931, the Oregon State Park Commission accepted the proposal, and Silver Falls State Park officially opened to the public in July 1933. Many of the signs still in existence in the park were originally erected by June Drake, and Drake Falls in the park was named after him.
June D. Drake married Eleanor Schoenfield in 1904. The couple's home in Silverton was the first in the town to be wired for electricity. The Drakes had two children, Charles Henry, born in 1909, and Ardith Maxine, born in 1915. In addition to his career as a photographer, June Drake was also a member of the Knights of Pythias and served as secretary of the Silverton Chamber of Commerce, chief of the Silverton Fire Department, and a member of the city council. He also founded the Silverton Historical Society in 1930.
Photographic negatives in the collection are not available for direct access due to fragility. Researchers are asked to use digitized versions available online in OHS Digital Collections. Contact library staff for assistance.
The Oregon Historical Society Research Library also holds the June D. Drake papers, Mss 1617, which contain Drake's personal and family papers, writings, and the Drake Bros. Studio records and photography registers.
Other collections of photographs taken by June D. Drake can be found at the Silverton Country Historical Society in Silverton, Oregon, and the archives of Silver Falls State Park.
Collection consists of approximately 2,918 original photographic prints and 3,800 original glass and acetate negatives taken by photographer June D. Drake of Silverton, Oregon, as well as 3,042 copy prints made by the Oregon Historical Society from the original negatives. The bulk of the collection consists of photographs that Drake took of various towns in Oregon, including Silverton, Mount Angel (including Mount Angel Abbey), and Salem, Oregon, from approximately 1900-1953. These photographs depict street scenes, businesses, schools, churches, and other town buildings, as well as significant events and celebrations. There are also a number of photographs that Drake took of the area that became Silver Falls State Park, as well as a large number of portrait photographs taken by Drake from about 1900-1952, including both studio and informal portraits.
Other subjects represented in the collection include transportation and agriculture in Oregon; the lumber industry around Silverton, including the Silver Falls Timber Company and the Silverton Lumber Company; Homer Davenport and his family in Silverton; the Chemawa Indian School near Silverton, and other portraits of Native Americans from the area; the military in Oregon, including the Oregon State Militia during World War I and World War II; and photographs of animals. The collection also includes six photograph albums; of note is an album titled "A History of Silverton, Oregon, and its environs," which contains detailed descriptions from 1863 to the 1930s, and includes places of business, worship, and study, among other scenes. There are also a number of photographs of various artifacts and other objects collected by Drake to document the history of Silverton.
Photographs in this collection that date prior to 1900 were originally taken by other photographers, including Silverton photographer William L. Jones, and reprinted by June D. Drake, who owned many of Jones's negatives.
The following articles can be found in the "Genealogy -- Drake, Charles Wesley family" Vertical File at the Oregon Historical Society Research Library:
"June Drake Dies in Portland," Silverton Appeal-Tribune, 1969 July 3.
"Silverton Turns Back One Century," Oregon Journal, August 4, 1954, feature section, page 1.
"Dedication Ceremony Draws Thousands," Silverton Appeal-Tribune, July 21, 1983. Reprint of July 28, 1933, article.
"Silverton Businessmen Welcome Visitors to Park Dedication Sunday," Silver Falls State Park Magazine, Volume 1 (July 1933).
Davenport, Homer, 1867-1912--Photographs; Jones, William L.
Mt. Angel Abbey (Saint Benedict, Or.)--Photographs; Drake Bros. Studio (Silverton, Or.)
Drake family--Photographs; Davenport family--Photographs
Mount Angel (Or.)--Photographs; Salem (Or.)--Photographs; Silverton (Or.)--Photographs
Agriculture--Oregon--Photographs; Animals--Photographs; Indians of North America--Oregon--Photographs; Lumber trade--Oregon--Photographs; Lumber trade--Oregon--Silverton--Photographs; Transportation--Oregon--Photographs; Waterfalls--Oregon--Photographs
Oregon; Photographs
photographs; glass plate negatives
- June D. Drake family photographs, circa 1900-1930; Series 1; 34 photographic prints
  This series contains photographs Drake took of his children and parents, as well as of his father's farm in Silverton, Oregon. Includes self-portraits.
  - Ardith Maxine and Charles Henry Drake, 1919-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charles Wesley Drake, Fannie Aurora Milster Drake, and June D. Drake, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - June D. Drake, 1901; 1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Charles Wesley Drake's farm, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Portraits, circa 1889-1952; Series 2; 1,111 photographic prints
  Arranged into two subseries: Subseries 2.1, Unidentified sample studio portraits, and Subseries 2.2, Other portraits.
  - Unidentified sample studio portraits, 1908-1916; undated; Subseries 2.1
    Arranged alphabetically.
    This subseries contains unidentified sample portraits that June D. Drake used for commercial purposes for Drake Bros. Studio., some from 1908-1916 and others undated. The bulk of these portraits were taken in the studio.
    - Album 678-2: Studio samples of infants and toddlers, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Album 678-3: Studio samples of families, adults, and children, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Album 678-4: Studio samples of sports teams and staff of the Pacific Star, 1908-1916 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Album 678-6: Studio samples of groups, families, and children, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Individuals--Infants, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Groups--Children--Boys, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Groups--Children--Girls, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Groups--Children--Girls and boys, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Groups--Couples, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Groups--Families, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Groups--Men, undated (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
    - Groups--Women, undated (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
    - Groups--Women and men, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Other portraits, circa 1889-1952; Subseries 2.2
    This subseries contains other portraits, mostly identified, that were taken by June D. Drake in the studio and in more informal settings, such as the outdoors, homes, and workplaces. Many of these photographs are undated.
    - Individuals--A - B, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Individuals--Benston, Carl, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Individuals--C - E, 1911; undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Individuals--F - H, 1900-1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Individuals--Grover [Mr.], undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Individuals--Grover [Mr.] (oversize material), undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Individuals--Harper, Jay (circus clown), undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Individuals--I - L, 1913; undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Individuals--M - O, undated; Includes hand-colored photograph. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Individuals--P - S, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Individuals--Pederson, N., undated; Hand-colored photograph. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Individuals--T - Z, 1900; undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Includes some members of the Adolf Wolf family.
    - Individuals--Waldo, Daniel, undated; Copy print made from an oil painting originally made in 1890. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Individuals--Ying, Jan, undated; Includes hand-colored photograph. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Groups--Families--A - E, circa 1900-1952 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Groups--Organizations and clubs--Woodsmen of the World (oversize material), 1914 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Groups--Organizations and clubs--Sons of Norway Lodge (oversize material), circa 1921 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Families--F - M, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Families--N - Z, 1910-1935 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Families--N - Z (oversize material), undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Families--Police chief (unidentified) and family, circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Families--Sande, Earl family, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Families--Wolf, Adolf family, circa 1889-1910 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      All photographs taken prior to 1900 were originally taken by an unidentified photographer, possibly William L. Jones, and copied later by June D. Drake.
    - Families--Woodward, Myron family, circa 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Other groups--African American boxers, circa 1909 (Box 3, Folder 20a)
      Studio portrait of the African American boxers and sparring partners Jack Johnson, heavyweight boxer of the world from 1908-1915, and Joe "The Barbados Demon" Wolcott, possibly taken in Portland, Oregon.
    - Other groups--Medical portraits, undated (Box 3, Folder 20b)
      Taken by June D. Drake to document the progression and treatment of various skin diseases and other medical problems in patients.
    - Unidentified portraits--Children, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified portraits--Children (oversize material), undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified portraits--Children (oversize material), 1928 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified portraits--Families, undated (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
    - Unidentified portraits--Groups, 1901-1950 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Unidentified portraits--Groups (oversize material), undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified portraits--Men, 1928; undated (Box 3, Folder 25-27)
    - Unidentified portraits--Men (oversize material), 1900-1915 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified portraits--Men (oversize material), 1928 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified portraits--Women, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Unidentified portraits--Wedding parties, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Unidentified portraits--Wedding parties (oversize material), undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Locations, 1860-1953; Series 3; 2,864 photographic prints
  This series is arranged into five subseries: Subseries 3.1, Silverton; Subseries 3.2, Mount Angel; Subseries 3.3, Salem; Subseries 3.4, Silver Falls State Park; and Subseries 3.5, Other locations.
  - Silverton, 1860-1953; Subseries 3.1
    This series contains photographs of buildings, businesses, churches, fires, floods, organizations, schools, street scenes, and other views of Silverton, Oregon, taken by June D. Drake. There are also some views of Silver Creek as it runs through the town, as well as a photographic history of Silverton from 1862-1951 that was assembled by Drake toward the end of his professional career.
    - Album 678-1: "A History of Silverton and its environs...", 1862-1951 (Box 4, Folder A-C)
      Photograph album assembled by June D. Drake to document the history and physical changes of the town of Silverton from 1862-1951. All photographs taken prior to 1900 in the album were originally taken by William L. Jones and reprinted by Drake. This album was disbound in 2004 and the photographs and captions were foldered separately; a photocopy of the original album before it was disbound is included in Box 4, Folder C. See also Box 3, Folder 3 of the June D. Drake papers, Mss 1617, for a hand-written history and photo captions meant to accompany this photograph album.
    - Album 678-5: "Souvenir Letter, Silverton, Ore.", 1907 (Box 4, Folder D)
      Photomechanical prints published by Drake Bros. Studio in 1907 of photographs of Silverton, Oregon, taken by June D. Drake.
    - Bands, 1879-1940 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      All photographs taken prior to 1900 were originally taken by William L. Jones and reprinted by June D. Drake.
    - Buildings--Fraternal organizations, circa 1915-1952 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Buildings--Hospital, circa 1915-1947 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Buildings--Public, circa 1900-1946 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--A - C, circa 1900-1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Includes photograph of the Adolf Wolf store.
    - Businesses--Identified by name--A. L. Adams Flight Training, circa 1925-1929 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--Adolf Wolf Store (oversize material), 1890 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--Allen Brothers Garage, circa 1925-1926 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--Banks, circa 1909-1925 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--Banks--People's Bank (oversize material), circa 1915 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--D - F, 1891-circa 1921 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--Drake Bros. Studio, 1908-circa 1920 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--Eastman Brothers Manufacturing and Silverton Blow Pipe Co., circa 1910-1925 (Box 4, Folder 9-11)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--Fischers' Flouring Mills, circa 1900-1928 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--G - L, circa 1900-1925 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--M - O, circa 1898-1937 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--P - S, circa 1910-1947 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--Portland General Electric, 1910-1928 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--Beginning with "Silverton", circa 1900-1950 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--Silverton Creamery & Ice Co., circa 1908-1920 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--Silverton Greenhouse, circa 1908-1920 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Businesses--Identified by name--T - Z, circa 1890-1930 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Businesses--Unidentified--Auto shop - Butcher, circa 1890-1946 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Businesses--Unidentified--Dry goods stores - Jewelry stores, circa 1910-1920 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      Includes photographs of Chinese mercantile store.
    - Businesses--Unidentified--Dry goods stores (oversize material), circa 1920 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Businesses--Unidentified--Livery stable - Popcorn vendor, circa 1910-1920 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Businesses--Unidentified--Professional offices, circa 1900-1950 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Includes photographs of offices of dentist, doctor, lawyer, and real estate agents.
    - Businesses--Unidentified--Professional offices (oversize material), circa 1900-1915 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Businesses--Unidentified--Restaurants - Sporting goods, circa 1910-1920 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Businesses--Unidentified--Street cleaner, circa 1910 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Includes image of Mr. Cavendar, Silverton street cleaner.
    - Cemeteries and monuments, 1894-1953 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Churches--Catholic, 1914; circa 1925 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Churches--Christian, circa 1908-1922 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Churches--Lutheran, circa 1900-1927 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Churches--Methodist, circa 1908-1952 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Churches--Rural, 1910; 1935; 1951 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Churches--Other, circa 1922-1925 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Fire department, 1915; circa 1925; 1948; 1950 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Fires--Drake Bros. Studio, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Fires--Opera House, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Organizations and clubs--Identified, 1911-1940 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Organizations and clubs--Identified--Grand Army of the Republic (GAR) Veterans (oversize material), 1891 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Organizations and clubs--Unidentified, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Parks--Coolidge & McClaine Park, 1909-1945 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Parks--Coolidge & McClaine Park--Swimming, 1924; circa 1945 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Residences--A - D, circa 1909-1925 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Residences--H - W, circa 1895-1951 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Residences--Unidentified, circa 1900-1931 (Box 5, Folder 23-24)
    - Residences--Unidentified garden, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Residences--Unidentified interiors, circa 1900; 1915 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Road building--Railroad construction--N. Water Street, circa 1905 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Road building--1st and Park, circa 1912 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Includes photograph of African American workers.
    - Road building--McClaine Street, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Road building--Silverton Hills, circa 1920 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Road building--Water Street, 1911-1912; circa 1915; circa 1940 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Road building--Unidentified streets, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Road building--Gravel quarry, S. Water Street, circa 1910-1912; 1936 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Schools--Elementary--Activities, circa 1917 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Schools--Elementary--Buildings, 1862-1925 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Schools--Elementary--Buildings--Eugene Field School (oversize material), circa 1924 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Schools--Elementary--Classes, 1890-1946 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Schools--High school/Junior high--Activities, circa 1918-1928 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Schools--High school/Junior high--Buildings, 1907-1948 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Schools--High school/Junior high--Buildings--Interiors, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Schools--High school/Junior high--Classes, circa 1915-1948 (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
    - Schools--High school/Junior high--Faculty, circa 1908; 1925; 1927; 1931 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Schools--High school/Junior high--Sports--Baseball, circa 1910-1935 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Schools--High school--Sports--Basketball--Boys, 1908-1934 (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
    - Schools--High school--Sports--Basketball--Girls, 1908; 1916; circa 1920 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Schools--High school--Sports--Football, circa 1915; circa 1920; 1925; circa 1926 (Box 6, Folder 21-26)
    - Schools--High school--Sports--Football, undated (Box 6, Folder 27-30)
      Includes photographs of football coach Allan DeLay.
    - Schools--High school--Sports--Golf and track, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Schools--Rural--Buildings, 1910; 1911; 1951 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Schools--Rural--Classes, 1888-1918 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Silver Creek--Bridges, 1890-1920 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Silver Creek--Dams, 1901-1946 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Silver Creek--Floods, 1917; 1949 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Silver Creek--Winter views, 1909-1930 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Silver Creek--Views, 1923-1925 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Special events--Eagles convention, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Special events--Fourth of July parades, 1890-1918 (Box 14, Folder 16-22)
    - Special events--Modern Woodsmen of America parade and picnic, 1909 June 5 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Special events--May Day celebration, 1915; 1924-1925 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Special events--Silverton Community Fair, circa 1925 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Special events--Silverton Fruit Show, 1924 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Special events--Other--Identified, 1911-1954 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      Includes photographs of Oswald West speaking in Silverton; Ezra Meeker; a public burning of an effigy of Kaiser Wilhelm on November 11, 1918; and the Silverton Centennial in 1954, among other subjects.
    - Special events--Other--Unidentified, 1901-1925 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Sports--Baseball--McGinnis Field, circa 1930 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Sports--Baseball--Unidentified, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Sports--Baseball--Teams, circa 1925; 1930 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Sports--Basketball, 1910; 1913-1914 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Sports--Golf--Silverton Country Club, 1910; 1925; 1935 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Sports--Track and field, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Views--General, 1860-1925 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Views--General (oversize material), 1909 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Views--From East Hill, circa 1900-1923 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Views--From West Hill, circa 1912-1925 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Views--Snow scenes, 1909 January; 1911 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Views--Snow scenes (oversize material), 1909-1911 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Views--Street scenes, circa 1914-1942 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Views--Street scenes--Main Street, 1863-1947 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Views--Street scenes--Main Street (oversize material), 1929 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Views--Street scenes--Water Street, 1883-1950 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Mount Angel, 1890-1940; Subseries 3.2